{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This \"people of the flint\" were the target of missionary efforts by Johannes Megapolensis [[yoh-HAH-ness meh-guh-poh-LEN-siss]] and earlier battled Hurons under the command of Samuel de Champlain. Due to claiming lands along a namesake river valley west of the Hudson River, this group was known as the Keepers of the Eastern Door. For ten points, name this member tribe of the Iroquois [[IH-roh-kwoy]] Confederacy, known in popular culture for an incorrectly attributed hairstyle in which the sides of the head are shaven.",
      "answer": [
        "Mohawks or Kanienʼkehá꞉ka",
        "Keepers of the Eastern Door before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "As punishment for smoking, Deccan [[DEH-kan]] sultan Malik Ambar poured this substance into the ears and mouths of criminals. The Piazza Fontana bombings occurred during a tumultuous time in Italian history known as the \"Years of [this substance].\" This substance's presence in Roman toys and plumbing has been speculated as a cause of the fall of the Roman Empire due to widespread impotence and ill health effects. For ten points, name this toxic metal symbolized Pb.",
      "answer": [
        "Lead",
        "Pb before mentioned",
        "Years of Lead",
        "Anni di piombo"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During a performance in this country of the ballet Spartacus by Aram Khachaturian [[kah-chah-TOO-ree-ahn]], Leonid Yakobson [[YAH-kohb-sun]] abandoned the traditional pointe technique during a performance at the Bolshoi Theatre. Ethnically Polish dancer Vaslav Nijinsky [[nih-JIN-skee]] helped popularize a ballet company named for this nation originally founded by Sergei Diaghilev [[dee-AH-geh-lef]]. Unrest occurred during the ballet The Rite of Spring, composed by, for ten points, what nation's composer, Igor Stravinsky?",
      "answer": "Russia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pinaka and Shiranga are this type of weapon in Hindu myth, in which Arjuna [[ar- JOO-nah]] also fights with one of these weapons made by Brahma called Gandiva [[gahn- DEE-vah]]. Hou Yi [[HOH-YEE]] uses one of these weapons in Chinese myth to eliminate nine of the ten suns. The constellation Sagittarius is named after Chiron's [[KY-rons]] role in teaching the use of these weapons to Achilles. Medieval tales abound with legends of users of these weapons from Sherwood Forest. For ten points, name this ranged weapon often featured in mythology.",
      "answer": "Bow and Arrows 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas Young helped decipher this writing system by identifying that cartouches [[kar-TOO-shes]] were used to enclose royal names. Demotic [[dee-MAH-tik]] was a simplified version of Hieratic [[hy-RAH-tik]] cursive, which derived from this writing system. Jean-François Champollion [[shahm-pohl-YOHN]] deciphered this script using an object which depicted a decree in this system as well as Ancient Greek. The Rosetta Stone helped decipher, for ten points, what pictographic writing system of Ancient Egypt?",
      "answer": "Egyptian Hieroglyphs or Hieroglyphics"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an effort to map this river in the 19th century, Breton explorer Auguste Pavie [[pah-VEE]] led a namesake mission with a convoy of elephants. During the first days of the Tet Offensive, the Vietcong attempted to seize all major towns in South Vietnam along this river. Cambodia, Laos, Thailand, and Vietnam formed a commission to maintain the natural integrity of, for ten points, what river of Southeast Asia?",
      "answer": [
        "Mekong River",
        "Mekong River Commission"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Near the end of this decade, Link Wray released the song “Rumble,” and Alan Freed’s career tanked due to the Payola scandal. Number one hits in this decade included “The Ballad of Davy Crockett,” “Love Me Tender,” and “La Bamba.” At this decade’s end, a plane crash called “The Day the Music Died” resulted in the deaths of Richie Valens, The Big Bopper, and Buddy Holly. For ten points, name this decade in which the rock-and-roll hit \"Heartbreak Hotel\" became a number one hit for Elvis Presley.",
      "answer": "1950s"
    },
    {
      "question": "A victim of one of these attacks attempted to fold one thousand origami cranes to rid herself of a perpetual illness caused by one of these events, the orders for which were transmitted by General Thomas T. Handy. The Flying Fortress Enola Gay dropped a payload known as the \"Little Boy\" during the first of these events. For ten points, name these attacks by the United States on Japan, the only recorded nuclear bombings in history.",
      "answer": [
        "Atomic Bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki",
        "Atomic Bombings of Japan",
        "\"Nuclear\" in place of \"Atomic\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "To criticize a man holding this position, Buzz Windrip, Doremus Jessup uses the periodical The Vermont Vigilance in the Sinclair Lewis novel, It Can't Happen Here. Prior to the events of Philip K. Dick's The Man in the High Castle, the successor of John Nance Garner, John W. Bricker, held this political position but failed to prevent an Axis occupation of North America. Phyllis Wheatley wrote \"To his Excellency General Washington\" about a holder of, for ten points, what executive position?",
      "answer": [
        "President of the United States of America",
        "American President",
        "U.S. in place of United States 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A passive walkout-turned-uprising in one of these places in Vorkuta [[vor-KOO-tah]] occurred in response to a mass influx of Ukrainians and the arrest of the repressive NKVD head Lavrentiy Beria [[law-REN-tee BEH-ree-ah]]. The Khrushchev Thaw led to the rehabilitation of many prisoners held in these camps first created by Lenin during the Russian Civil War. Many of the political opponents of the Great Purge were sent to, for ten points, what Soviet forced labor camps prominent in the Stalinist period?",
      "answer": [
        "Gulags",
        "Glávnoje upravlénije lageréj 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, the Creel Committee sent out “four minute men” to encourage people to buy war bonds, and during this war, the USFA encouraged “Meatless Mondays.” The Sedition Act passed during this war caused Eugene V. Debs to be jailed for encouraging draft-dodging. A president urged the U.S to enter this war to “make the world safe for democracy.” For ten points, name this war in which the United States sent \"doughboys\" to fight in the trenches.",
        "answer": [
          "World War One or the First World War",
          "the Great War",
          "or Weltkrieg"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the war, this man was appointed head of the War Emergency Division to deport supposed disloyal foreigners. He later served as the first Director of the FBI from 1924 to 1972.",
        "answer": "John Edgar Hoover"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "It's not Portugal, but The Lusiads inspired this nation's opera L'Africaine [[lah-free- KEHN]], about the historical Vasco da Gama. A member of this nation's Les Six [[LEH SEE]] was inspired by the martyrdom of a convent of nuns to write his Dialogues of the Carmelites. The composer of The Carnival of the Animals was from this nation, as was the composer of Clair de Lune. For ten points, name this European nation, home to composers like Camille Saint-Saëns [[kah-MEEL san-SAHN]] and Claude Debussy [[klohd deh-byoo-SEE]].",
        "answer": [
          "France",
          "First French Empire",
          "Second French Empire",
          "French Second Republic",
          "French Third Republic"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Georges Bizet [[bee-ZEH]], another French composer, set this opera in the historical bull-fighting scene of the south of Spain.",
        "answer": "Carmen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A peasant rebellion in this nation led by Skipper Clement was put down by the noble Johan Rantzau [[RAHNT-zow]] during the Count's Feud. Håkon VI [[HAH-kohn the SIXTH]] of Norway married this kingdom's Queen Margaret, leading to the formation of the Kalmar Union. The German Empire seized this country's province of Schleswig [[SHLESS-vig]] in a brief 19th century conflict. For ten points, name this Scandinavian nation that once governed Sweden and Norway from its capital, Copenhagen.",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Denmark or Kongeriget Danmark",
          "the Danish Realm",
          "or Danmarks Rige"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1970s, Denmark awarded home rule to what largest non-continental island on Earth?",
        "answer": [
          "Greenland",
          "Kalaallit Nunaat",
          "or Grønland 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This oratorio was based on a text compiled from the Coverdale Psalter and King James Bible by Charles Jennens. Part one of this oratorio depicts the salvation of Isaiah, and that scene in this work is punctuated by And the Glory of the Lord. A popular legend states that George II began the tradition of standing during this piece's Hallelujah Chorus. For ten points, name this oratorio often performed at Christmas, written by George Frideric Handel.",
        "answer": "Messiah"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Although he often performed in London, Handel's Messiah debuted on this island, which had been controlled by the English since 1603.",
        "answer": "Ireland or Eire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group intentionally sparked the Regina [[ruh-JY-nah]] Riots in an attempt to crush a mass protest of unemployed men. This group was able to successfully infiltrate the Communist Party of its nation, and one of this group's most notable accomplishments was capturing stagecoach robber Bill Miner. The nickname of this group derives from their now- defunct standard of riding horses. For ten points, name this police force that is responsible for civil control in Canada.",
        "answer": [
          "Mounties",
          "Royal Canadian Mounted Police",
          "RCMP"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Regina Riots of 1935 effectively ended this \"trek\" of unemployed men known as \"On-to-[this Ontario city].\"",
        "answer": "Ottawa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one of these artworks, a woman labeled \"America First\" reads a children's book titled Adolf the Wolf to impressionable kids. One of these artworks depicts a turtle known as \"O Grab Me\" biting a New Englander holding a barrel labeled \"Super Fine.\" The two symbols of the American political parties, the donkey and elephant, were first introduced through this medium. For ten points, name these graphics that depict public figures, usually expressing the artist's opinion.",
        "answer": "Political Cartoons"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Nast, perhaps America's most well-known political cartoonist, gained notoriety for his criticism of \"Boss\" Tweed, the leader of what New York political machine that was infamous for its corruption?",
        "answer": [
          "Tammany Hall or Tammany Society",
          "Society of St. Tammany",
          "or Sons of St. Tammany",
          "the Columbian Order 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A poet from this nation named Pulci [[POOL-chee]] retells an account of Charlemagne’s paladins, Roland [[roh-LAHND]] and Renauld [[reh-NOHD]] who convert the title Morgante [[mor-GAHN-teh]] to Christianity. William of Baskerville solves a murder in a Benedictine monastery in this country in The Name of the Rose by Umberto Eco [[EH-koh]]. Cesare Borgia's [[CHEH-zeh-reh BOR-zhahs]] military exploits inspired Niccolo Machiavelli to write The Prince, in, for ten points, what is now what country?",
        "answer": [
          "Italy",
          "Italian Republic",
          "Italia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dario Fo wrote the Italian-language play Isabella, Three Sailing Ships and a Con Man to demystify the narrative around this 15th-century explorer.",
        "answer": [
          "Christopher Columbus",
          "Cristoforo Colombo",
          "or Cristóbal Colón"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "England's first ambassador to this nation, Thomas Roe, failed to gain special trading privileges in Surat [[soo-RAHT]]. The Afghani Sur Empire temporarily usurped control from this country until the regent Hemu [[HEE-moo]] lost the Second Battle of Panipat [[PAN-ee- pat]]. The rulers of this empire claimed direct descent from Tamerlane, and under Aurangzeb [[oh-RAHNG-zehb]] this empire conquered much of the Deccan [[DEH-kan]] Plateau. Shah Jahan and Akbar ruled, for ten points, what Muslim empire of the Indian subcontinent?",
        "answer": "Mughal Empire or Mughals"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shah Jahan constructed what palatial complex for his diseased wife, Mumtaz [[MOOM-tahz]]?",
        "answer": "Taj Mahal"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "California Gold Rush",
      "prompt": "Concerning the California gold rush, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "General term for communities that exploded in population in a short period of time during the Gold Rush.",
          "answer": "Boomtown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname of those who participated in the Gold Rush, based on a specific year.",
          "answer": "49er"
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular clothing item manufactured by Levi Strauss.",
          "answer": [
            "Blue Jeans",
            "Denim Jeans"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mill at which the discovery of gold sparked the Gold Rush.",
          "answer": "Sutter's Mill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Simple method used by miners to extract gold from streams by using a namesake iron apparatus.",
          "answer": "Panning"
        },
        {
          "question": "Eastern California mountain range which contained many of the goldfields targeted by prospectors.",
          "answer": "Sierra Nevada Mountains or Sierra Nevadas"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. author who used it as the backdrop for his short story \"The Luck of Roaring Camp.\"",
          "answer": "Bret Harte or Francis Bret Harte"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ship carrying three tons of gold which sank off the Carolina coast during an 1857 hurricane.",
          "answer": "SS Central America 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Third Crusade",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Third Crusade, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Holy city whose capture led to the call for the Third Crusade.",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Lion-Hearted\" king who led the English after the death of his father, Henry II.",
          "answer": "King Richard I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kurdish sultan whose conquests prompted the late 12th century Crusade.",
          "answer": "Saladin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ismaili sect and anti-Crusader faction in Syria who now names the English term for a \"trained killer.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Assassins",
            "Hashashins"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German emperor who drowned in a river while heading to fight the Sultanate of Rum.",
          "answer": [
            "Frederick Barbarossa",
            "Frederick I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Port whose successful siege by Guy [[GEE]] of Jerusalem allowed the Crusaders to launch incursions into the Holy Land.",
          "answer": "Acre ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Twin-peaked volcano near which a Crusader army was destroyed, prompting the Third Crusade two years later.",
          "answer": [
            "Hattin or Horns of Hattin",
            "Battle of Hattin",
            "or Battle of the Horns of Hattin",
            "Hittin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City which names a treaty which recognized Muslim control of Jerusalem in exchange for safe Christian pilgrimage.",
          "answer": [
            "Treaty of Jaffa",
            "Treaty of Ramla 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5 Ancient Monuments of the World"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Ancient World was full of magnificent structures, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the the ancient world was full of magnificent structures, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City that contained the Pharos, or Great Lighthouse, and a massive library.",
          "answer": "Alexandria"
        },
        {
          "question": "City on the Tigris and Euphrates that possessed a legendary Hanging Garden.",
          "answer": "Babylon or Bābilim"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of elaborate wonder built at Halicarnassus and named for a wealthy Satrap.",
          "answer": [
            "Mausoleum at Halicarnassus",
            "Tomb of Mausolus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Anatolian city where the Temple of Artemis was housed.",
          "answer": [
            "Ephesus",
            "Éphesos",
            "or Efes"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancient Hebrew king who supposedly built the First Temple in Jerusalem.",
          "answer": "Solomon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of the Nabataeans [[nah-buh-TAY-ens]] built into a desert mountain in Jordan.",
          "answer": "Petra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Enormous Mahayana Buddhist temple in Central Java, Indonesia.",
          "answer": "Borobudur or Candi Borobudur"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second-century BC Buddhist cave system in Maharashtra that features surviving paintings from the period.",
          "answer": "Ajanta Caves or Buddhist Caves of Ajanta 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Jerome Connor created a tribute to the more than 600 nuns who nursed soldiers during this conflict, and Loreta Janeta Velázquez likely masqueraded as a male soldier during this conflict. The only woman to ever receive the Medal of (20 pts)",
        "Honor, Mary Walker, served as a surgeon during this war, as did the founder of the American Red Cross and \"Angel of the Battlefield,\" (10 pts)",
        "Clara Barton. For ten points, name this war, during which Belle Boyd provided valuable information to Stonewall Jackson."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United States Civil War",
        "War Between the States",
        "War of Northern Aggression",
        "American",
        "U.S. in place of \"United States\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) \"Mad Jack\" Churchill entered battle carrying one of these instruments, using it to signal attack orders to his fellow commandos during operations. James Reid was executed for playing this instrument during the Battle of Culloden [[kuh-LAH-den]] in (20 pts)",
        "the Jacobite [[JAK-oh-bite]] Rising, with the British brandishing this instrument as a \"weapon of war.\" Contemporary historian George Buchanan reports that this aerophonic instrument replaced the trumpet in warfare during in the 1600s. The Highlanders (10 pts)",
        "of Scotland introduced, for ten points, which woodwind instrument?"
      ],
      "answer": "Bagpipes"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1979, the Wetzel [[VEHT-zull]] family escaped East Germany using one of these objects after years of planning. The first-ever intercontinental ranged weapon used this technology and was known as Fu-Go (20 pts)",
        "by the Japanese. French brothers Joseph-Michel and Jacques-Étienne Montgolfier [[mohnt-gahl-FYEH]] undertook the first manned flight of this technology, which was used for reconnaissance at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Fleurus [[floo-ROO]]. For ten points, name these inflatable transports which Nadar used to take aerial photographs of Paris."
      ],
      "answer": "Hot-Air Balloon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The case [this U.S. state] v. Mitchell held that the government could not force a state to lower the voting age to eighteen. This state's largest city performed a mock- evacuation during Operation Greenlight after officials deemed the (20 pts)",
        "Willamette [[wih-LAM-et]] Valley a possible Soviet bombing target. In 2021, this state's eastern counties, including Malheur [[MALL-heer]], Sherman, and Grant, passed a measure promoting secession to form \"Greater (10 pts)",
        "Idaho.\" For ten points, name this U.S. state governed from Salem."
      ],
      "answer": "Oregon 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Myths about this location were discredited by Frantz Funck-Brentano [[foonk- bren-TAH-noh]]. A large plaster elephant was placed at this location by Napoleon, though it was replaced by the July Column. (20 pts)",
        "Palloy the Patriot demolished this location, which was defended by Bernard Rene de Launay [[reh-neh-duh-law-NAY]] alongside the Swiss Guard who were cut down by a (10 pts)",
        "mob. For ten points, name this Parisian fortress and prison destroyed at the beginning of the French Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "The Bastille Saint-Antoine"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "The largest bronze example of this type of artwork depicts the controversial conquistador who committed a massacre of the Acoma Pueblo, Governor Juan de Oñate [[oh-NYAH-teh]]. One sculpture of this type known as the \"Quadriga,\" (*) depicting a vehicle driven by the Goddess of Victory, tops the Brandenburg Gate. Frederic Remington's Bronco Buster, a sculpture of this type, depicts a (*) cowboy of the Old West. Ancient Greece's Rampin Rider is an early example of, for ten points, what type of statue?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Equestrian Statue",
        "answers describing subjects \"being on horseback\"",
        "Chariot Statue"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Fears of this person's influence led people to believe that Black men would knock down white women on this person's \"Tuesdays.\" Pauli Murray and this person worked to appeal for Odell Waller, though he was still executed in Virginia. Mary (20 pts)",
        "McLeod Bethune and this person often walked arm-in-arm. This woman resigned from the Daughters of the American Revolution after Marian (10 pts)",
        "Anderson was not allowed to sing in Constitution Hall. For ten points, name this Depression-era First Lady."
      ],
      "answer": "Eleanor Roosevelt or Anna Eleanor Roosevelt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A character in this novel, based on a historical warlord also known as Xuande [[SHWAHN-DEH]], throws his infant son to the ground after General Zhao Yun [[ZHOW-YUN]] risks his life to save him during the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Changban [[CHAHNG- BAHN]]. The Battle of Red Cliffs appears in this novel which relates the campaigns of Cao Cao [[KOW-KOW]] (10 pts)",
        "and Zhuge Liang [[TCHOO-guh LYAHNG]]. Luo Guanzhong [[LWOH GWAHN-ZHOHNG]] wrote, for ten points, what historical “Romance” set during a namesake period of Chinese history?"
      ],
      "answer": "Romance of the Three Kingdoms or Sānguó Yǎnyì 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
    }
  ]
}